hi everyone today we are continuing our
implementation of make more now in the
last lecture we implemented the multier
perceptron along the lines of benj 2003
for character level language modeling so
we followed this paper took in a few
characters in the past and used an MLP
to predict the next character in a
sequence so what we'd like to do now is
we'd like to move on to more complex and
larger neural networks like recurrent
neural networks and their variations
like the grw lstm and so on now before
we do that though we have to stick
around the level of malalia perception
on for a bit longer and I'd like to do
this because I would like us to have a
very good intuitive understanding of the
activations in the neural net during
training and especially the gradients
that are flowing backwards and how they
behave and what they look like and this
is going to be very important to
understand the history of the
development of these architectures
because we'll see that recurr neural
networks while they are very expressive
in that they are a universal
approximator and can in principle
Implement uh all the algorithms uh we'll
see that they are not very easily
optimizable with the first order
gradient based techniques that we have
available to us and that we use all the
time and the key to understanding why
they are not optimizable easily is to
understand the the activations and the
gradients and how they behave during
training and we'll see that a lot of the
variants since recur neural networks
have tried to improve that situation and
so that's the path that we have to take
and uh let's get started so the starting
code for this lecture is largely the
code from before but I've cleaned it up
a little bit so you'll see that we are
importing
all the torch and math plb utilities
we're reading in the words just like
before these are eight example words
there's a total of 32,000 of them here's
a vocabulary of all the lowercase
letters and the special dot token here
we are reading the data set and
processing it and um creating three
splits the train Dev and the test split
now in MLP this is the identical same
MLP except you see that I removed a
bunch of magic numbers that we had here
and instead we have the dimensionality
of the embedding space of the characters
and the number of hidden units in the
hidden layer and so I've pulled them
outside here uh so that we don't have to
go and change all these magic numbers
all the time we have the same neural net
with 11,000 parameters that we optimize
now over 200,000 steps with a batch size
of 32 and you'll see that I refactor I
refactored the code here a little bit
but there are no functional changes I
just created a few extra variables a few
more comments and I removed all the
magic numbers and otherwise is the exact
same thing then when we optimize we saw
that our loss looked something like this
we saw that the train and Val loss were
about
2.16 and so on here I refactored the uh
code a little bit for the evaluation of
arbitary splits so you pass in a string
of which split you'd like to evaluate
and then here depending on train Val or
test I index in and I get the correct
split and then this is the forward pass
of the network and evaluation of the
loss and printing it so just making that
nicer uh one thing that you'll notice
here is I'm using a decorator torch.
nograd which you can also um look up and
read the documentation of basically what
this decorator does on top of a function
is that whatever happens in this
function is assumed by uh torch to never
require any gradients so it will not do
any of the bookkeeping that it does to
keep track of all the gradients in
anticipation of an eventual backward
pass it's it's almost as if all the
tensors that get created here have a
required grad of false and so it just
makes everything much more efficient
because you're telling torch that I will
not call that backward on any of this
computation and you don't need to
maintain the graph under the hood so
that's what this does and you can also
use a context manager uh with torch du
nograd and you can look those
up then here we have the sampling from a
model um just as before just a for
Passive neural nut getting the
distribution sent from it adjusting the
context window and repeating until we
get the special end token and we see
that we are starting to get much nicer
looking words simple from the model it's
still not amazing and they're still not
fully name like uh but it's much better
than what we had with the BAM
model so that's our starting point now
the first thing I would like to
scrutinize is the
initialization I can tell that our
network is very improperly configured at
initialization and there's multiple
things wrong with it but let's just
start with the first one look here on
the zeroth iteration the very first
iteration we are recording a loss of 27
and this rapidly comes down to roughly
one or two or so so I can tell that the
initialization is all messed up because
this is way too high in training of
neural Nets it is almost always the case
that you will have a rough idea for what
loss to expect at initialization and
that just depends on the loss function
and the problem setup in this case I do
not expect 27 I expect a much lower
number and we can calculate it together
basically at initialization what we like
is that um there's 27 characters that
could come next for any one training
example at initialization we have no
reason to believe any characters to be
much more likely than others and so we'd
expect that the propy distribution that
comes out initially is a uniform
distribution assigning about equal
probability to all the 27
characters so basically what we' like is
the probability for any character would
be roughly 1 over 20
7 that is the probability we should
record and then the loss is the negative
log probability so let's wrap this in a
tensor and then then we can take the log
of it and then the negative log
probability is the loss we would expect
which is 3.29 much much lower than 27
and so what's happening right now is
that at initialization the neural nut is
creating probity distributions that are
all messed up some characters are very
confident and some characters are very
not confident confident and then
basically what's happening is that the
network is very confidently wrong and uh
that that's what makes it um record very
high loss so here's a smaller
four-dimensional example of the issue
let's say we only have four characters
and then we have logits that come out of
the neural net and they are very very
close to zero then when we take the
softmax of all zeros we get
probabilities there are a diffused
distribution so sums to one and is
exactly
uniform and then in this case if the
label is say two it doesn't actually
matter if this if the label is two or
three or one or zero because it's a
uniform distribution we're recording the
exact same loss in this case 1.38 so
this is the loss we would expect for a
four-dimensional example and now you can
see of course that as we start to
manipulate these logits uh we're going
to be changing the law here so it could
be that we lock out and by chance uh
this could be a very high number like
you know five or something like that
then case we'll record a very low loss
because we're assigning the correct
probability at initialization by chance
to the correct label much more likely it
is that some other dimension will have a
high uh logit and then what will happen
is we start to record much higher loss
and what can come what can happen is
basically the logits come out like
something like this you know and they
take on Extreme values and we record
really high loss
um for example if we have to 4. random
of four so these are uniform um sorry
these are normally distributed um
numbers uh four of
them then here we can also print the
logits probabilities that come out of it
and the loss and so because these logits
are near zero for the most part the loss
that comes out is is okay uh but suppose
this is like times 10
now you see how because these are more
extreme values it's very unlikely that
you're going to be guessing the correct
bucket and then you're confidently wrong
and recording very high loss if your
loes are coming out even more
extreme you might get extremely insane
losses like infinity even at
initialization
um so basically this is not good and we
want the loges to be roughly zero um
when the network is initialized in fact
the lits can don't have to be just zero
they just have to be equal so for
example if all the logits are one then
because of the normalization inside the
softmax this will actually come out okay
but by symmetry we don't want it to be
any arbitrary positive or negative
number we just want it to be all zeros
and record the loss that we expect at
initialization so let's now concretely
see where things go wrong in our example
here we have the initialization let me
reinitialize the neuronet and here let
me break after the very first iteration
so we only see the initial loss which is
so that's way too high and intuitively
now we can expect the variables involved
and we see that the logits here if we
just print some of
these if we just print the first row we
see that the Lo just take on quite
extreme values and that's what's
creating the fake confidence in
incorrect answers and makes the loss um
get very very high so these loes should
be much much closer to zero so now let's
think through how we can achieve logits
coming out of this neur not to be more
closer to zero you see here that loes
are calculated as the hidden states
multip by W2 plus B2 so first of all
currently we're initializing B2 as
random values uh of the right size but
because we want roughly zero we don't
actually want to be adding a bias of
random numbers so in fact I'm going to
add a times zero here to make sure that
B2 is just um basically zero at
initialization and second this is H
multip by W2 so if we want logits to be
very very small then we would be
multiplying W2 and making that
smaller so for example if we scale down
W2 by 0.1 all the elements then if I do
again just a very first iteration you
see that we are getting much closer to
what we expect so rough roughly what we
want is about
3.29 this is
4.2 I can make this maybe even
smaller 3.32 okay so we're getting
closer and closer now you're probably
wondering can we just set this to zero
then we get of course exactly what we're
looking for um at
initialization and the reason I don't
usually do this is because I'm I'm very
nervous and I'll show you in a second
why you don't want to be setting W's or
weights of a neural nut exactly to zero
um you you usually want it to be small
numbers instead of exactly zero um for
this output layer in this specific case
I think it would be fine but I'll show
you in a second where things go wrong
very quick quickly if you do that so
let's just go with
0.01 in that case our loss is close
enough but has some entropy it's not
exactly zero it's got some little
entropy and that's used for symmetry
breaking as we'll see in a second the
logits are now coming out much closer to
zero and everything is well and good so
if I just erase these and I now take
away the break
statement we can run the optimization
with this new initialization and let's
just see
what losses we record okay so I let it
run and you see that we started off good
and then we came down a
bit the plot of the loss uh now doesn't
have this hockey shape appearance um
because basically what's happening in
the hockey stick the very first few
iterations of the loss what's happening
during the optimization is the
optimization is just squashing down the
logits and then it's rearranging the
logits so basically we took away this
easy part of the loss function where
just the the weights were just being
shrunk down and so therefore we're we
don't we don't get these easy gains in
the beginning and we're just getting
some of the hard gains of training the
actual neural nut and so there's no
hockey stick appearance so good things
are happening in that both number one
losset initialization is what we expect
and the the loss doesn't look like a
hockey stick and this is true for any
neuron that you might train um and
something to look out for and second the
loss that came out is actually quite a
bit improved unfortunately I erased what
we had here before I believe this was 2.
um2 and this was this was 2.16 so we get
a slightly improved result and the
reason for that is uh because we're
spending more Cycles more time
optimizing the neuronet actually instead
of just uh spending the first several
thousand iterations probably just
squashing down the
weights because they are so way too high
in the beginning in the initialization
so something to look out for and uh
that's number one now let's look at the
second problem let me reinitialize our
neural net and let me reintroduce The
Brak statement so we have a reasonable
initial loss so even though everything
is looking good on the level of the loss
and we get something that we expect
there's still a deeper problem looking
inside this neural net and its
initialization so the logits are now
okay the problem now is with the values
of H the activations of the Hidden
States now if we just visualize this
Vector sorry this tensor h it's kind of
hard to see but the problem here roughly
speaking is you see how many of the
elements are one or negative 1 now
recall that torch. 10 the 10 function is
a squashing function it takes arbitrary
numbers and it squashes them into a
range of negative 1 and one and it does
so smoothly so let's look at the
histogram of H to get a better idea of
the distribution of the values inside
this tensor we can do this
first well we can see that H is 32
examples and 200 activations in each
example we can view it as1 to stretch it
out into one large
vector and we can then call two list to
convert this into one large python list
of floats and then we can pass this into
PLT doist for histogram and we say we
want 50 bins and a semicolon to suppress
a bunch of output we don't
want so we see this histogram and we see
that most the values by far take on
value of netive one and one so this 10 H
is very very active and we can also look
at basically why that is we can look at
the pre activations that feed into the
10 and we can see that the distribution
of the pre activations are is very very
broad these take numbers between -5 and
15 and that's why in a torure 10
everything is being squashed and capped
to be in the range of negative 1 and one
and lots of numbers here take on very
extreme values now if you are new to
neural networks you might not actually
see this as an issue but if you're well
vered in the dark arts of back
propagation and then having an intuitive
sense of how these gradients flow
through a neural net you are looking at
your distribution of 10h activations
here and you are sweating so let me show
you why we have to keep in mind that
during back propagation just like we saw
in microad we are doing backward passs
starting at the loss and flowing through
the network backwards in particular
we're going to back propagate through
this torch.
10h and this layer here is made up of
200 neurons for each one of these
examples and uh it implements an
elementwise 10 so let's look at what
happens in 10h in the backward pass we
can actually go back to our previous uh
microgr code in the very first lecture
and see how we implemented 10 AG we saw
that the input here was X and then we
calculate T which is the 10 age of X so
that's T and T is between 1 and 1 it's
the output of the 10 H and then in the
backward pass how do we back propagate
through a 10 H we take out that grad um
and then we multiply it this is the
chain rule with the local gradient which
took the form of 1 - t ^2 so what
happens if the outputs of your t h are
very close to1 or 1 if you plug in t one
here you're going to get a zero
multiplying out. grad no matter what
out. grad is we are killing the gradient
and we're stopping effectively the back
propagation through this 10 unit
similarly when t is1 this will again
become zero and out that grad just stops
and intuitively this makes sense because
this is a 10h
neuron and what's happening is if its
output is very close to one then we are
in the tail of this
10 and so changing basically the
input is not going to impact the output
of the 10 too much because it's it's so
it's in a flat region of the 10 H and so
therefore there's no impact on the loss
and so so indeed the the weights and the
biases along with the 10h neuron do not
impact the loss because the output of
the 10 unit is in the flat region of the
10 and there's no influence we can we
can be changing them whatever we want
however we want and the loss is not
impacted that's so that's another way to
justify that indeed the gradient would
be basically zero it
vanishes indeed uh when T equals zero we
get one times out that grad so when the
10 h takes on exactly value of zero then
out grad is just passed through so
basically what this is doing right is if
T is equal to zero then this the 10 unit
is uh sort of inactive and uh gradient
just passes through but the more you are
in the flat tails the more the gradient
is squashed so in fact you'll see that
the the gradient flowing through 10 can
only ever decrease and the amount that
it decreases is um proportional through
a square here um depending on how far
you are in the flat tail so this 10 H
and so that's kind of what's Happening
Here and through this the concern here
is that if all of these um outputs H are
in the flat regions of negative 1 and
one then the gradients that are flowing
through the network will just get
destroyed at this
layer now there is some redeeming
quality here and that we can actually
get a sense of the problem here as
follows I wrote some code here and
basically what we want to do here is we
want to take a look at H take the the
absolute value and see how often it is
in the in a flat uh region so say
greater than
099 and what you get is the following
and this is a Boolean tensor so uh in
the Boolean tensor you get a white if
this is true and a black if this is
false and so basically what we have here
is the 32 examples and 200 hidden
neurons and we see that a lot of this is
white and what that's telling us is that
all these 10h neurons were very very
active and uh they're in a flat tail and
so in all these cases uh the back the
backward gradient would get uh
destroyed now we would be in a lot of
trouble if for for any one of these 200
neurons if it was the case that the
entire column is white because in that
case we have what's called a dead neuron
and this is could be a 10 neuron where
the initialization of the weights and
the biases could be such that no single
example ever activates uh this 10h in
the um sort of active part of the 10age
if all the examples land in the tail
then this neuron will never learn it is
a dead neuron and so just scrutinizing
this and looking for Columns of
completely white uh we see that this is
not the case so uh I don't see a single
neuron that is all of uh you know white
and so therefore it is the case that for
every one of these 10h neurons uh we do
have some examples that activate them in
the uh active part of the 10 and so some
gradients will flow through and this
neuron will learn and the neuron will
change and it will move and it will do
something but you can sometimes get get
yourself in cases where you have dead
neurons and the way this manifests is
that um for 10h neuron this would be
when no matter what inputs you plug in
from your data set this 10h neuron
always fir
completely one or completely negative
one and then it will just not learn
because all the gradients will be just
zeroed out uh this is true not just for
10 but for a lot of other nonlinearities
that people use in neural networks so we
certainly used 10 a lot but sigmoid will
have the exact same issue because it is
a squashing neuron and so the same will
be true for sigmoid uh but um but um you
know um basically the same will actually
apply to sigmoid the same will also
apply to reu
so reu has a completely flat region here
below zero so if you have a reu neuron
then it is a pass through um if it is
positive and if it's if the
preactivation is negative it will just
shut it off since the region here is
completely flat then during back
propagation uh this would be exactly
zeroing out the gradient um like all of
the gradient would be set exactly to
zero instead of just like a very very
small number depending on how positive
or negative T is and so you can get for
example a dead reu neuron and a dead reu
neuron would basically look like
basically what it is is if a neuron with
a reu nonlinearity never activates so
for any examples that you plug in in the
data set it never turns on it's always
in this flat region then this re neuron
is a dead neuron its weights and bias
will never learn they will never get a
gradient because the neuron never
activated and this can sometimes happen
at initialization uh because the way and
a biases just make it so that by chance
some neurons are just forever dead but
it can also happen during optimization
if you have like a too high of learning
rate for example sometimes you have
these neurons that get too much of a
gradient and they get knocked out off
the data
manifold and what happens is that from
then on no example ever activates this
neuron so this neuron remains dead
forever so it's kind of like a permanent
brain damage in a in a mind of a network
and so sometimes what can happen is if
your learning rate is very high for
example and you have a neural net with
neurons you train the neuron net and you
get some last loss but then actually
what you do is you go through the entire
training set and you forward um your
examples and you can find neurons that
never activate they are dead neurons in
your network and so those neurons will
will never turn on and usually what
happens is that during training these
Rel neurons are changing moving Etc and
then because of a high gradient
somewhere by chance they get knocked off
and then nothing ever activates them and
from then on they are just dead uh so
that's kind of like a permanent brain
damage that can happen to some of these
neurons these other nonlinearities like
leyu will not suffer from this issue as
much because you can see that it doesn't
have flat Tails you'll almost always get
gradients and uh elu is also fairly uh
frequently used um it also might suffer
from this issue because it has flat
parts so that's just something to be
aware of and something to be concerned
about and in this case we have way too
many um activations AG that take on
Extreme values and because there's no
column of white I think we will be okay
and indeed the network optimizes and
gives us a pretty decent loss but it's
just not optimal and this is not
something you want especially during
initialization and so basically what's
happening is that uh this H
preactivation that's floating to 10 H
it's it's too extreme it's too large
it's creating very um it's creating a
distribution that is too saturated in
both sides of the 10 H and it's not
something you want because it means that
there's less training uh for these
neurons because they update um less
frequently so how do we fix this well H
preactivation is MCAT which comes from C
so these are uniform gsan but then it's
multiply by W1 plus B1 and H preact is
too far off from zero and that's causing
the issue so we want this reactivation
to be closer to zero very similar to
what we had with
logits so here
we want actually something very very
similar now it's okay to set the biases
to very small number we can either
multiply by 0 01 to get like a little
bit of entropy um I sometimes like to do
that um just so that there's like a
little bit of variation and diversity in
the original initialization of these 10
H neurons and I find in practice that
that can help optimization a little bit
and then the weights we can also just
like squash so let's multiply everything
by 0.1
let's rerun the first batch and now
let's look at this and well first let's
look
here you see now because we multiply dou
by 0.1 we have a much better histogram
and that's because the pre activations
are now between 1.5 and 1.5 and this we
expect much much less white okay there's
no white so basically that's because
there are no neurons that saturated
above 99 in either direction so this
actually a pretty decent place to be um
maybe we can go up a little
bit sorry am I am I changing W1 here so
maybe we can go to 0
2 okay so maybe something like this is
is a nice distribution so maybe this is
what our initialization should be so let
me now
erase
these and let me starting with
initialization let me run the full
optimization
without the break and uh let's see what
we get okay so the optimization finished
and I re the loss and this is the result
that we get and then just as a reminder
I put down all the losses that we saw
previously in this lecture so we see
that we actually do get an improvement
here and just as a reminder we started
off with a validation loss of 2.17 when
we started by fixing the softmax being
confidently wrong we came down to 2.13
and by fixing the 10h layer being way
too saturated we came down to 2.10
and the reason this is happening of
course is because our initialization is
better and so we're spending more time
doing productive training instead of um
not very productive training because our
gradients are set to zero and uh we have
to learn very simple things like uh the
overconfidence of the softmax in the
beginning and we're spending Cycles just
like squashing down the weight Matrix so
this is illustrating um basically
initialization and its impacts on
performance uh just by being aware of
the internals of these neural net and
their activations their gradients now
we're working with a very small Network
this is just one layer multi-layer
perception so because the network is so
shallow the optimization problem is
actually quite easy and very forgiving
so even though our initialization was
terrible the network still learned
eventually it just got a bit worse
result this is not the case in general
though once we actually start um working
with much deeper networks that have say
50 layers uh things can get uh much more
complicated and uh these problems stack
up and so you can actually get into a
place where the network is basically not
training at all if your initialization
is bad enough and the deeper your
network is and the more complex it is
the less forgiving it is to some of
these errors and so um something to
definitely be aware of and uh something
to scrutinize something to plot and
something to be careful with and um yeah
okay so that's great that that worked
for us but what we have here now is all
these magic numbers like0 2 like where
do I come up with this and how am I
supposed to set these if I have a large
neural net with lots and lots of layers
and so obviously no one does this by
hand there's actually some relatively
principled ways of setting these scales
um that I would like to introduce to you
now so let me paste some code here that
I prepared just to motivate the
discussion of
this so what I'm doing here is we have
some random input here x that is drawn
from a gan and there's 1,000 examples
that are 10 dimensional
and then we have a waiting layer here
that is also initialized using caution
just like we did here and we these
neurons in the hidden layer look at 10
inputs and there are 200 neurons in this
hidden layer and then we have here just
like here um in this case the
multiplication X multip by W to get the
pre activations of these
neurons and basically the analysis here
looks at okay suppose these are uniform
gion and these weights are uniform gion
if I do X W and we forget for now the
bias and the
nonlinearity then what is the mean and
the standard deviation of these gions so
in the beginning here the input is uh
just a normal Gan distribution mean zero
and the standard deviation is one and
the standard deviation again is just the
measure of a spread of the
gion but then once we multiply here and
we look at the um histogram of Y we see
that the mean of course stays the same
it's about zero because this is a
symmetric operation but we see here that
the standard deviation has expanded to
three so the input standard deviation
was one but now we've grown to three and
so what you're seeing in the histogram
is that this Gan is
expanding and so um we're expanding this
Gan um from the input and we don't want
that we want most of the neural net to
have relatively similar activations uh
so unit gion roughly throughout the
neural net and so the question is how do
we scale these W's to preserve the uh um
to preserve this distribution to uh
remain
aan and so intuitively if I multiply
here uh these elements of w by a larger
number let's say by
five then this gsan gross and gross in
standard deviation so now we're at 15 so
basically these numbers here in the
output y take on more and more extreme
values but if we scale it down like .2
then conversely this Gan is getting
smaller and smaller and it's shrinking
and you can see that the standard
deviation is 6 and so the question is
what do I multiply by here to exactly
preserve the standard deviation to be
one and it turns out that the correct
answer mathematically when you work out
through the variance of uh this
multiplication here is that you are
supposed to divide by the square root of
the fan in the fan in is the basically
the uh number of input elements here 10
so we are supposed to divide by 10
square root and this is one way to do
the square root you raise it to a power
of 0. five that's the same as doing a
square root so when you divide by the um
square root of 10 then we see that the
output caution it has exactly standard
deviation of one now unsurprisingly a
number of papers have looked into how
but to best initialized neural networks
and in the case of multilayer
perceptrons we can have fairly deep
networks that have these nonlinearity in
between and we want to make sure that
the activations are well behaved and
they don't expand to infinity or Shrink
all the way to zero and the question is
how do we initialize the weights so that
these activations take on reasonable
values throughout the network now one
paper that has studied this in quite a
bit of detail that is often referenced
is this paper by King hatal called
delving deep into rectifiers now in this
case they actually study convolution
neur neurals and they study especially
the reu nonlinearity and the p
nonlinearity instead of a 10h
nonlinearity but the analysis is very
similar and um basically what happens
here is for them the the relu
nonlinearity that they care about quite
a bit here is a squashing function where
all the negative numbers are simply
clamped to zero so the positive numbers
are pass through but everything negative
is just set to zero and because uh you
are basically throwing away half of the
distribution they find in their analysis
of the forward activations in the neural
that you have to compensate for that
with a
gain and so here they find that
basically when they initialize their
weights they have to do it with a zero
mean Gan whose standard deviation is
square < TK of 2 over the Fanon what we
have here is we are initializing gashin
with the square root of Fanon this NL
here is the Fanon so what we have is
sare root of one over the Fanon because
we have the division here
now they have to add this factor of two
because of the reu which basically
discards half of the distribution and
clamps it at zero and so that's where
you get an additional Factor now in
addition to that this paper also studies
not just the uh sort of behavior of the
activations in the forward pass of the
neural net but it also studies the back
propagation and we have to make sure
that the gradients also are well behaved
and so um because ultimately they end up
updating our parameters and what they
find here through a lot of analysis that
I invite you to read through but it's
not exactly approachable what they find
is basically if you properly initialize
the forward pass the backward pass is
also approximately initialized up to a
constant factor that has to do with the
size of the number of um hidden neurons
in an early and a late
layer and uh but basically they find
empirically that this is not a choice
that matters too much now this timing
initialization is also implemented in
pytorch so if you go to torch. and then.
init documentation you'll find climing
normal and in my opinion this is
probably the most common way of
initializing neural networks now and it
takes a few keyword arguments here so
number one it wants to know the mode
would you like to normalize the
activations or would you like to
normalize the gradients to to be always
uh gsh in with zero mean and a unit or
one standard deviation and because they
find in the paper that this doesn't
matter too much most of the people just
leave it as the default which is Fan in
and then second passing the nonlinearity
that you are using because depending on
the nonlinearity we need to calculate a
slightly different gain and so if your
nonlinearity is just um linear so
there's no nonlinearity then the gain
here will be one and we have the exact
same uh kind of formula that we've come
up here but if the nonlinearity is
something else we're going to get a
slightly different gain and so if we
come up here to the top we see that for
example in the case of reu this gain is
a square root of two and the reason it's
a square root because in this
paper you see how the two is inside of
the square root so the gain is a square
root of two in the case of linear or
identity we just get a gain of one in a
case of 10 H which is what we're using
here the advised gain is a 5 over3 and
intuitively why do we need a gain on top
of the initialization is because 10 just
like reu is a contractive uh
transformation so that means is you're
taking the output distribution from this
matrix multiplication and then you are
squashing it in some way now reu
squashes it by taking everything below
zero and clamping it to zero 10 also
squashes it because it's a contractive
operation it will take the Tails and it
will squeeze them in and so in order to
fight the squeezing in we need to boost
the weights a little bit so that we
renormalize everything back to standard
unit standard deviation so that's why
there's a little bit of a gain that
comes out now I'm skipping through this
section A little bit quickly and I'm
doing that actually intentionally and
the reason for that is because about 7
years ago when this paper was written
you had to actually be extremely careful
with the activations and ingredients and
their ranges and their histograms and
you had to be very careful with the
precise setting of gains and the
scrutinizing of the nonlinearities used
and so on and everything was very
finicky and very fragile and to be very
properly arranged for the neural nut to
train especially if your neural nut was
very deep but there are a number of
modern innovations that have made
everything significantly more stable and
more well behaved and it's become less
important to initialize these networks
exactly right and some of those modern
Innovations for example are residual
connections which we will cover in the
future the use of a number of uh
normalization uh layers like for example
batch normalization layer normalization
group normalization we're going to go
into a lot of these as well and number
three much better optimizers not just
stochastic gradient descent the simple
Optimizer we're basically using here but
a slightly more complex optimizers like
ARS prop and especially Adam and so all
of these modern Innovations make it less
important for you to precisely calibrate
the neutralization of the neural net all
that being said in practice uh what
should we do in practice when I
initialize these neurals I basically
just uh normalize my weights by the
square root of the Fanon uh so basically
uh roughly what we did here is what I do
now if we want to be exactly accurate
here we and go by um in it of uh timing
normal this is how it would implemented
we want to set the standard deviation to
be gain over the square root of fan in
right so to set the standard deviation
of our weights we will proceed as
follows basically when we have a torch.
Ranon and let's say I just create a th
numbers we can look at the standard
deviation of this and of course that's
one that's the amount of spread let's
make this a bit bigger so it's closer to
one so that's the spread of the Gan of
zero mean and unit standard deviation
now basically when you take these and
you multiply by
say2 that basically scales down the Gan
and that makes it standard deviation 02
so basically the number that you
multiply by here ends up being the
standard deviation of this caution so
here this is a um standard deviation
point2 caution here when we sample our
W1 but we want to set the standard
deviation to gain over square root of
fan mode which is Fanon so in other
words we want to mul mly by uh gain
which for 10 H is 5
over3 5 over3 is the gain and then
times
um or I guess sorry
divide uh square root of the fan in and
in this example here the fan in was 10
and I just noticed that actually here
the fan in for W1 is is actually an
embed times block size which as you all
recall is actually 30 and that's because
each character is 10 dimensional but
then we have three of them and we can
catenate them so actually the fan in
here was 30 and I should have used 30
here probably but basically we want 30
uh square root so this is the number
this is what our standard deviation we
want to be and this number turns out to
be3 whereas here just by fiddling with
it and looking at the distribution and
making sure it looks okay uh we came up
with 02 and so instead what we want to
do here is we want to make the standard
deviation b
um 5 over3 which is our gain
divide this
amount times2 square root and these
brackets here are not that uh necessary
but I'll just put them here for clarity
this is basically what we want this is
the timing in it in our case for a 10h
nonlinearity and this is how we would
initialize the neural net and so we're
multiplying by .3 instead of multiplying
by
.2 and so we can we can initialize this
way and then we can train the neural net
and see what we get okay so I trained
the neural net and we end up in roughly
the same spot so looking at the
validation loss we now get 2.10 and
previously we also had 2.10 there's a
little bit of a difference but that's
just the randomness of the process I
suspect but the big deal of course is we
get to the same spot but we did not have
to introduce any um magic numbers that
we got from just looking at histograms
and guessing checking we have something
that is semi- principled and will scale
us to uh much bigger networks and uh
something that we can sort of use as a
guide so I mentioned that the precise
setting of these initializations is not
as important today due to some Modern
Innovations and I think now is a pretty
good time to introduce one of those
modern Innovations and that is batch
normalization so bat normalization came
out in uh 2015 from a team at Google and
it was an extremely impact paper because
it made it possible to train very deep
neuron Nets quite reliably and uh it
basically just worked so here's what
bash rization does and let's implement
it
um basically we have these uh hidden
States H preact right and we were
talking about how we don't want these uh
these um preactivation states to be way
too small because the then the 10 H is
not um doing anything but we don't want
them to be too large because then the 10
H is saturated in fact we want them to
be roughly roughly Gan so zero mean and
a unit or one standard deviation at
least at
initialization so the Insight from the
bachor liation paper is okay you have
these hidden States and you'd like them
to be roughly Gan then why not take the
hidden States and uh just normalize them
to be
Gan and it sounds kind of crazy but you
can just do that because uh
standardizing hidden States so that
their unit caution is a perfect ly
differentiable operation as we'll soon
see and so that was kind of like the big
Insight in this paper and when I first
read it my mind was blown because you
can just normalize these hidden States
and if you'd like unit Gan States in
your network uh at least initialization
you can just normalize them to be unit
gion so uh let's see how that works so
we're going to scroll to our
preactivation here just before they
enter into the 10h now the idea again is
remember we're trying to make these
roughly Gan and that's because if these
are way too small numbers then the 10 H
here is kind of inactive but if these
are very large numbers then the 10 H is
way too saturated and gr is no flow so
we'd like this to be roughly goshan so
the Insight in Bat normalization again
is that we can just standardize these
activations so they are exactly Gan so
here H
preact has a shapee of 32 by 200 32
examples by 200 neurons in the hidden
layer so basically what we can do is we
can take H pract and we can just
calculate the mean um and the mean we
want to calculate across the zero
Dimension and we want to also keep them
as true so that we can easily broadcast
this so the shape of this is 1 by 200 in
other words we are doing the mean over
all the uh elements in the
batch and similarly we can calculate the
standard deviation of these
activations and that will also be 1 by
200 now in this paper they have
the uh sort of prescription here and see
here we are calculating the mean which
is just taking uh the average
value of any neurons activation and then
the standard deviation is basically kind
of like um this the measure of the
spread that we've been using which is
the distance of every one of these
values away from the mean and that
squared and
averaged that's the that's the variance
and then if you want to take the
standard deviation you would square root
the variance to get the standard
deviation so these are the two that
we're calculating and now we're going to
normalize or standardize these X's by
subtracting the mean and um dividing by
the standard deviation so basically
we're taking in pract and we
subtract the mean
and then we divide by the standard
deviation this is exactly what these two
STD and mean are calculating
oops sorry this is the mean and this is
the variance you see how the sigma is a
standard deviation usually so this is
Sigma Square which the variance is the
square of the standard
deviation so this is how you standardize
these values and what this will do is
that every single neuron now and its
firing rate will be exactly unit Gan on
these 32 examples at least of this batch
that's why it's called batch
normalization we are normalizing these
batches and then we could in principle
train this notice that calculating the
mean and your standard deviation these
are just mathematical formulas they're
perfectly differentiable all of this is
perfectly differentiable and we can just
train this the problem is you actually
won't achieve a very good result with
this and the reason for that
is we want these to be roughly Gan but
only at initialization uh but we don't
want these be to be forced to be Garian
always we we'd like to allow the neuron
net to move this around to potentially
make it more diffuse to make it more
sharp to make some 10 neurons maybe be
more trigger more trigger happy or less
trigger happy so we'd like this
distribution to move around and we'd
like the back propagation to tell us how
the distribution should move around and
so in addition to this idea of
standardizing the activations that any
point in the network uh we have to also
introduce this additional component in
the paper here described as scale and
shift and so basically what we're doing
is we're taking these normalized inputs
and we are additionally scaling them by
some gain and offsetting them by some
bias to get our final output from this
layer and so what that amounts to is the
following we are going to allow a batch
normalization gain to be initialized at
just uh once
and the ones will be in the shape of 1
by n
hidden and then we also will have a BN
bias which will be torch. zeros and it
will also be of the shape n by 1 by n
hidden and then here the BN gain will
multiply
this and the BN bias will offset it
here so because this is initialized to
one and this to
zero at initialization each neurons
firing values in this batch will be
exactly unit gion and will have nice
numbers no matter what the distribution
of the H pract is coming in coming out
it will be un Gan for each neuron and
that's roughly what we want at least at
initialization um and then during
optimization we'll be able to back
propagate into BN gain and BM bias and
change them so the network is given the
full ability to do with this whatever it
wants uh
internally here we just have to make
sure sure that we um include these in
the parameters of the neural nut because
they will be trained with back
propagation so let's initialize this and
then we should be able to
train and then we're going to also copy
this line which is the batch
normalization layer here on a single
line of code and we're going to swing
down here and we're also going to do the
exact same thing at test time
here so similar to train time we're
going to normalize uh and then scale and
that's going to give us our train and
validation
loss and we'll see in a second that
we're actually going to change this a
little bit but for now I'm going to keep
it this way so I'm just going to wait
for this to converge okay so I allowed
the neural nut to converge here and when
we scroll down we see that our
validation loss here is 2.10 roughly
which I wrote down here and we see that
this is actually kind of comparable to
some of the results that we've achieved
uh previously now I'm not actually
expecting an improvement in this case
and that's because we are dealing with a
very simple neural nut that has just a
single hidden layer so in fact in this
very simple case of just one hidden
layer we were able to actually calculate
what the scale of w should be to make
these pre activations already have a
roughly Gan shape so the bat
normalization is not doing much here but
you might imagine that once you have a
much deeper neural nut that has lots of
different types of operations and
there's also for example residual
connections which we'll cover and so on
it will become basically very very
difficult to tune the scales of your
weight matrices such that all the
activations throughout the neural nut
are roughly gsen and so that's going to
become very quickly intractable but
compared to that it's going to be much
much easier to sprinkle batch
normalization layers throughout the
neural net so in particular it's common
to to look at every single linear layer
like this one one this is a linear layer
multiplying by a weight Matrix and
adding a bias or for example
convolutions which we'll cover later and
also perform basically a multiplication
with a weight Matrix but in a more
spatially structured format it's custom
it's customary to take these linear
layer or convolutional layer and append
a b rization layer right after it to
control the scale of these activations
at every point in the neural nut so we'd
be adding these bom layers throughout
the neural nut and then this controls
the scale of these AC ations throughout
the neural net it doesn't require us to
do uh perfect mathematics and care about
the activation distributions uh for all
these different types of neural network
uh Lego building blocks that you might
want to introduce into your neural net
and it significantly stabilizes uh the
training and that's why these uh layers
are quite popular now the stability
offered by bash normalization actually
comes at a terrible cost and that cost
is that if you think about what's
Happening Here something something
terribly strange and unnatural is
happening it used to be that we have a
single example feeding into a neural nut
and then uh we calculate its activations
and its loits and this is a
deterministic sort of process so you
arrive at some logits for this example
and then because of efficiency of
training we suddenly started to use
batches of examples but those batches of
examples were processed independently
and it was just an efficiency thing but
now suddenly in batch normalization
because of the normalization through the
batch we are coupling these examples
mathematically and in the forward pass
and the backward pass of a neural l so
now the hidden State activations H pract
in your log jits for any one input
example are not just a function of that
example and its input but they're also a
function of all the other examples that
happen to come for a ride in that batch
and these examples are sampled randomly
and so what's happening is for example
when you look at H pract that's going to
feed into H the hidden State activations
for for example for for any one of these
input examples is going to actually
change slightly depending on what other
examples there are in a batch and and
depending on what other examples happen
to come for a ride H is going to change
subtly and it's going to like Jitter if
you imagine sampling different examples
because the the statistics of the mean
and the standard deviation are going to
be impacted and so you'll get a Jitter
for H and you'll get a Jitter for
loits and you think that this would be a
bug uh or something undesirable but in a
very strange way this actually turns out
to be good in your Network training and
as a side effect and the reason for that
is that you can think of this as kind of
like a regularizer because what's
happening is you have your input and you
get your age and then depending on the
other examples this is jittering a bit
and so what that does is that it's
effectively padding out any one of these
input examples and it's introducing a
little bit of entropy and um because of
the padding out it's actually kind of
like a form of a data augmentation which
we'll cover in the future and it's kind
of like augmenting the input a little
bit and jittering it and that makes it
harder for the neural nut to overfit to
these concrete specific examples so by
introducing all this noise it actually
like Pats out the examples and it
regularizes the neural nut and that's
one of the reasons why uh deceivingly as
a second order effect uh this is
actually a regularizer and that has made
it harder uh for us to remove the use of
batch
normalization uh because basically no
one likes this property that the the
examples in the batch are coupled
mathematically and in the forward pass
and at least all kinds of like strange
uh results uh we'll go into some of that
in a second as well um and it leads to a
lot of bugs and um and so on and so no
one likes this property uh and so people
have tried to um deprecate the use of
bat normalization and move to other
normalization techniques that do not
couple the examples of a batch examples
are ler normalization instance
normalization group normalization and so
on and we'll come we'll come some these
uh later um but basically long story
short bat normalization was the first
kind of normalization layer to be
introduced it worked extremely well it
happened to have this regularizing
effect it stabilized training and people
have been trying to remove it and move
to some of the other normalization
techniques uh but it's been hard because
it it just works quite well and some of
the reason that it works quite well is
again because of this regular rizing
effect and because of the because it is
quite effective at um controlling the
activations and their
distributions uh so that's kind of like
the brief story of Bash normalization
and I'd like to show you one of the
other weird sort of outcomes of this
coupling so here's one of the strange
outcomes that I only glossed over
previously when I was evaluating the
loss on the validation set basically
once we've trained a neural net we'd
like to deploy it in some kind of a
setting and we'd like to be able to feed
in a single individual example and get a
prediction out from our neural net but
how do we do that when our neural net
now in a forward pass estimates the
statistics of the mean understand
deviation of a batch the neur lot
expects batches as an input now so how
do we feed in a single example and get
sensible results out and so the proposal
in the batch normalization paper is the
following what we would like to do here
is we would like to basically have a
step after training that uh calculates
and sets the bach uh mean and standard
deviation a single time over the
training set and so I wrote this code
here in interest of time and we're going
to call what's called calibrate the
bachor statistics and basically what we
do is torch torch. nograd telling
pytorch that none of this we will call
Dot backward on and it's going to be a
bit more efficient we're going to take
the training set get the pre activations
for every single training example and
then one single time estimate the mean
and standard deviation over the entire
training set and then we're going to get
B and mean and B and standard deviation
and now these are fixed numbers
estimating over the entire training set
and here instead of estimating it
dynamically we are going to instead here
use B and
mean and here we're just going to use B
and standard
deviation and so at test time we are
going to fix these clamp them and use
them during inference and
now you see that we get basically
identical result uh but the benefit that
we've gained is that we can now also
forward a single example because the
mean and standard deviation are now
fixed uh sort of tensor
that said nobody actually wants to
estimate this mean and standard
deviation as a second stage after neural
network training because everyone is
lazy and so this batch normalization
paper actually introduced one more idea
which is that we are can we can estimate
the mean and standard deviation in a
running man running manner during
training of the neuron nut and then we
can uh simply just have a single stage
of training and on the side of that
training we are estimating the running
mean and standard deviation so let's see
what that would look like let me
basically take the mean here that we are
estimating on the batch and let me call
this B and mean on the I
iteration um and then here this is BN
sdd um bnsd at I
okay uh and the mean comes here and the
STD comes here so so far I've done
nothing I've just uh moved around and I
created these EXT extra variables for
the mean and standard deviation and I've
put them here so so far nothing has
changed but what we're going to do now
is we're going to keep running mean of
both of these values during training so
let me swing up here and let me create a
BN meanor running and I'm going to
initialize it at uh
zeros and then BN STD running which I'll
initialize at
once because um in the beginning because
of the way we ized W1 uh and B1 H pract
will be roughly unit gion so the mean
will be roughly zero and a standard
deviation roughly one so I'm going to
initialize these that way but then here
I'm going to update these and in pytorch
um uh these uh mean and standard
deviation that are running uh they're
not actually part of the gradient based
optimization we're never going to derive
gradients with respect to them they're
they're updated on the side of training
and so what we're going to do here is
we're going to say with torch. nograd
telling pytorch that the update here is
not supposed to be building out a graph
because there will be no dot
backward but this running is basically
going to be
0.99 uh9 times the current
Value Plus 0.001 times the um this value
this new
mean and in the same way bnsd running
will be mostly what it used to be
but it will receive a small update in
the direction of what the current
standard deviation
is and as you're seeing here this update
is outside and on the side of the
gradient based optimization and it's
simply being updated not using gradient
scent it's just being updated using U
janky like Smooth um sort of uh running
mean
Manner and so while the network is
training and these pre activations are
sort of changing and shifting around
during during back propagation we are
keeping track of the typical mean and
standard deviation and we're estimating
them once and when I run
this now I'm keeping track of this in
the running Manner and what we're hoping
for of course is that the me BN meore
running and BN meore STD are going to be
very similar to the ones that we
calculated here before and that way we
don't need a second stage because we've
sort of combined the two stages and
we've put them on the side of each other
if you want to look at it that way and
this is how this is also implemented in
The Bash normalization uh layer impi
torch so during training um the exact
same thing will happen and then later
when you're using inference it will use
the estimated running mean of both the
mean and standard deviation of those
hidden States so let's wait for the
optimization to converge and hopefully
the running mean and standard deviation
are roughly equal to these two and then
we can simply use it here and we don't
need this stage of explicit calibration
at the end okay so the optimization
finished I'll rerun the explicit
estimation and then the B and mean from
the explicit estimation is here and B
and mean from the running estimation
during the during the optimization you
can see is very very similar it's not
identical but it's pretty
close and the same way BN STD is this
and BN STD running is this and so you
can see that once again they are fairly
similar values not identical but pretty
close and so then here instead of being
mean we can use the BN mean running
instead of bnsd we can use bnsd
running and uh hopefully the validation
loss will not be impacted too
much okay so it's basically identical
and this way we've eliminated the need
for this explicit stage of calibration
because we are doing it in line over
here okay so we're almost done with
batch normalization there are only two
more notes that I'd like to make number
one I've skipped a discussion over what
is this plus Epsilon doing here this
Epsilon is usually like some small fixed
number for example one5 by default and
what it's doing is that it's basically
preventing a division by zero in the
case that the variance over your batch
is exactly zero in that case uh here we
normally have a division by zero but
because of the plus Epsilon uh this is
going to become a small number in the
denominator instead and things will be
more well behaved so feel free to also
add a plus Epsilon here of a very small
number it doesn't actually substantially
change the result I'm going to skip it
in our case just because uh this is
unlikely to happen in our very simple
example here and the second thing I want
you to notice is that we're being
wasteful here and it's very subtle but
right here where we are adding the bias
into H preact these biases now are
actually useless because we're adding
them to the H preact but then we are
calculating the mean for every one of
these neurons and subtracting it so
whatever bias you add here is going to
get subtracted right here and so these
biases are not doing anything in fact
they're being subtracted out and they
don't impact the rest of the calculation
so if you look at b1. grad it's actually
going to be zero because it's being
subtracted out and doesn't actually have
any effect and so whenever you're using
bash normalization layers then if you
have any weight layers before like a
linear or a c or something like that
you're better off coming here and just
like not using bias so you don't want to
use bias and then here you don't want to
add it because it's that spirous instead
we have this B normalization bias here
and that b rization bias is now in
charge of the biasing of this
distribution instead of this B1 that we
had here originally and so uh basically
bash normalization layer has its own
bias and there's no need to have a bias
in the layer before it because that bias
is going to be subtracted out anyway so
that's the other small detail to be
careful with sometimes it's not going to
do anything catastrophic this B1 will
just be useless it will never get any
gradient uh it will not learn it will
stay constant and it's just wasteful but
it doesn't actually really uh impact
anything otherwise okay so I rearranged
the code a little bit with comments and
I just wanted to give a very quick
summary of The Bash normalization layer
we are using bash normalization to
control the statistics of activations in
the neural net it is common to sprinkle
bash normalization layer across the
neural net and usually we will place it
after layer that have multiplications
like for example a linear layer or
convolutional layer which we may cover
in the
future now the bat normalization
internally has parameters for the gain
and the bias and these are trained using
back propagation it also has two buffers
the buffers are the mean and the
standard deviation the running mean and
the running mean of the standard
deviation and these are not trained
using back propagation these are trained
using this uh janky update of kind of
like a running mean
update so
um these are sort of the parameters and
the buffers of Bator layer and then
really what it's doing is it's
calculating the mean and a standard
deviation of the activations uh that are
feeding into the Bator layer over that
batch then it's centering that batch to
be unit gion and then it's offsetting
and scaling it by the Learned bias and
gain and then on top of that it's
keeping track of the mean and standard
deviation of the inputs and it's
maintaining this running mean and
standard deviation and this will later
be used at inference so that we don't
have to reestimate the mean stand
deviation all the time and in addition
that allows us to basically forward
individual examples at test time so
that's the bash normalization layer it's
a fairly complicated layer um but this
is what it's doing internally now I
wanted to show you a little bit of a
real example so you can search resnet
which is a residual neural network and
these are common types of neural
networks used for image
classification and of course we haven't
come resnets in detail so I'm not going
to explain all the pieces of it but for
now just note that the image feeds into
a reset on the top here and there's many
many layers with repeating structure all
the way to predictions of what's inside
that image this repeating structure is
made up of these blocks and these blocks
are just sequentially stacked up in this
deep neural network now the code for
this uh the block basically that's used
and repeated sequentially in series is
called this bottleneck block bottleneck
block and there's a lot here this is all
pych and of course we haven't covered
all of it but I want to point out some
small pieces of it here in the init is
where we initialize the neuronet so this
code of block here is basically the kind
of stuff we're doing here we're
initializing all the layers and in the
forward we are specifying how the neuron
lot acts once you actually have the
input so this code here is along the
lines of what we're doing
here and now these blocks are replicated
and stacked up serially and that's what
a residual Network would be and so
notice What's Happening Here com one um
these are convolution layers and these
convolution layers basically they're the
same thing as a linear layer except
convolutional layers don't apply um
convolutional layers are used for images
and so they have SP structure and
basically this linear multiplication and
bias offset are done on patches instead
of math instead of the full input so
because these images have structure
spatial structure convolutions just
basically do WX plus b but they do it on
overlapping patches of the input but
otherwise it's WX plus
P then we have the norm layer which by
default here is initialized to be a bash
Norm in 2D so two- dimensional bash
normalization layer and then we have a
nonlinearity like reu so instead of uh
here they use reu we are using 10 in
this case but both both are just
nonlinearities and you can just use them
relatively interchangeably for very deep
networks re typically empirically work a
bit better so see the motif that's being
repeated here we have convolution bat
normalization reu convolution bat
normalization re Etc and then here this
is residual connection that we haven't
covered yet but basically that's the
exact same pattern we have here with we
have a weight layer like a convolution
or like a linear layer bash
normalization and then 10h which is
nonlinearity but basically a weight
layer a normalization layer and
nonlinearity and that's the motif that
you would be stacking up when you create
these deep neural networks exactly as
it's done here and one more thing I'd
like you to notice is that here when
they are initializing the com layers
like com 1 by one the depth for that is
right here and so it's initializing an
nn. Tod which is a convolution layer in
pytorch and there's a bunch of keyword
arguments here that I'm not going to
explain yet but you see how there's bias
equals false the bias equals false is
exactly for the same reason as bias is
not used in our case you see how I eras
the use of bias and the use of bias is
spous because after this weight layer
there's a bash normalization and The
Bash normalization subtracts that bias
and then has its own bias so there's no
need to introduce these spous parameters
it wouldn't hurt performance it's just
useless and so because they have this
motif of C Bast umbrell they don't need
a bias here because there's a bias
inside here so by the way this example
here is very easy to find just do
resonet pie
torch and uh it's this example here so
this is kind of like the stock
implementation of a residual neural
network in pytorch and uh you can find
that here but of course I haven't
covered many of these parts yet and I
would also like to briefly descend into
the definitions of these pytorch layers
and the the parameters that they take
now instead of a convolutional layer
we're going to look at a linear layer uh
because that's the one that we're using
here this is a linear layer and I
haven't cover covered convolutions yet
but as I mentioned convolutions are
basically linear layers except on
patches so a linear layer performs a WX
plus b except here they're calling the W
A
transpose um so to calcul WX plus b very
much like we did here to initialize this
layer you need to know the fan in the
fan out and that's so that they can
initialize this W this is the fan in and
the fan out so they know how how big the
weight Matrix should be you need to also
pass in whether you whether or not you
want a bias and if you set it to false
then no bias will be uh inside this
layer um and you may want to do that
exactly like in our case if your layer
is followed by a normalization layer
such as batch
Norm so this allows you to basically
disable a bias now in terms of the
initial ation if we swing down here this
is reporting the variables used inside
this linear layer and our linear layer
here has two parameters the weight and
the bias in the same way they have a
weight and a bias and they're talking
about how they initialize it by default
so by default P will initialize your
weights by taking the
Fanon and then um doing one over fanin
square root and then instead of a normal
distribution they are using a uniform
distribution
so it's very much the same thing but
they are using a one instead of 5 over
three so there's no gain being
calculated here the gain is just one but
otherwise is exactly one over the square
root of fan in exactly as we have
here so one over the square root of K is
the is the scale of the weights but when
they are drawing the numbers they're not
using a gussion by default they're using
a uniform distribution by default and so
they draw uniformly from negative of K
to squ of K
but it's the exact same thing and the
same motivation from for with respect to
what we've seen in this lecture and the
reason they're doing this is if you have
a roughly gsan input this will ensure
that out of this layer you will have a
roughly Gan output and you you basically
achieve that by scaling the weights by
one over the square root of fan in so
that's what this is
doing and then the second thing is the
bash normalization layer so let's look
at what that looks like in pytorch
so here we have a onedimensional b
normalization layer exactly as we are
using here and there are a number of
keyword arguments going into it as well
so we need to know the number of
features uh for us that is 200 and that
is needed so that we can initialize
these parameters here the gain the bias
and the buffers for the running uh mean
and standard
deviation then they need to know the
value of Epsilon here and by default
this is one5 you don't typically change
this too much then they need to know the
momentum
and the momentum here as they explain is
basically used for these uh running mean
and running standard deviation so by
default the momentum here is 0.1 the
momentum we are using here in this
example is
0.001 and basically rough you may want
to change this sometimes and roughly
speaking if you have a very large batch
size then typically what you'll see is
that when you estimate the mean and the
standard deviation for every single
batch size if it's large enough you're
going to get roughly the same result
and so therefore you can use slightly
higher momentum like
0.1 but for a batch size as small as 32
the mean and standard deviation here
might take on slightly different numbers
because there's only 32 examples we are
using to estimate the mean and standard
deviation so the value is changing
around a lot and if your momentum is 0.1
that that might not be good enough for
this value to settle and um converge to
the actual mean and standard deviation
over the entire training set and so
basically if your batch size is very
small uh momentum of 0.1 is potentially
dangerous and it might make it so that
the running uh mean and stand deviation
are is thrashing too much during
training and it's not actually
converging
properly uh aine equals true determines
whether this batch normalization layer
has these learnable Aline parameters the
uh the gain and the bias and this is
almost always kept to true I'm not
actually sure why you would want to
change this to false um
then track running stats is determining
whether or not B rization layer of
pytorch will be doing
this and um one reason you may you may
want to skip the running stats is
because you may want to for example
estimate them at the end as a stage two
like this and in that case you don't
want the bat normalization layer to be
doing all this extra compute that you're
not going to
use and uh finally we need to know which
device we're going to run this bash
normalization on a CPU or a GPU and what
the data type should be uh half
Precision single Precision double
precision and so
on so that's the bat normalization layer
otherwise they link to the paper is the
same formula we've implemented and
everything is the same exactly as we've
done
here okay so that's everything that I
wanted to cover for this lecture really
what I wanted to talk about is the
importance of understanding the
activations and the gradients and their
statistics in neural networks and this
becomes increasingly important
especially as you make your neural
networks bigger larger and deeper
we looked at the distributions basically
at the output layer and we saw that if
you have two confident mispredictions
because the activations are too messed
up at the last layer you can end up with
these hockey stick losses and if you fix
this you get a better loss at the end of
training because your training is not
doing wasteful work then we also saw
that we need to control the activations
we don't want them to uh you know squash
to zero or explode to infinity and
because that you can run into a lot of
trouble with all of these uh
nonlinearities and these neural Nets and
basically you want everything to be
fairly homogeneous throughout the neural
net you want roughly goshan activations
throughout the neural net let me talked
about okay if we want roughly Gan
activations how do we scale these weight
matrices and biases during
initialization of the neural nut so that
we don't get um you know so everything
is as controlled as
possible um so that give us a large
boost in Improvement and then I talked
about how that strategy is not actually
uh Poss for much much deeper neural nuts
because um when you have much deeper
neural nuts with lots of different types
of layers it becomes really really hard
to precisely set the weights and the
biases in such a way that the
activations are roughly uniform
throughout the neural nut so then I
introduced the notion of a normalization
layer now there are many normalization
layers that that people use in practice
bat normalization layer normalization
instance normalization group
normalization we haven't covered most of
them but I've introduced the first one
and also the one that I believe came out
first and that's called Bat
normalization and we saw how bat
normalization Works uh this is a layer
that you can sprinkle throughout your
deep neural net and the basic idea is if
you want roughly gsh in activations well
then take your activations and um take
the mean and the standard deviation and
Center your data and you can do that
because the centering operation is
differentiable but and on top of that we
actually had to add a lot of bells and
whistles and that gave you a sense of
the complexities of the batch
normalization layer because now we're
centering the data that's great but
suddenly we need the gain and the bias
and now those are
trainable and then because we are
coupling all of the training examples
now suddenly the question is how do you
do the inference where to do to do the
inference we need to now estimate these
um mean and standard deviation once uh
or the entire training set and then use
those at inference but then no one likes
to do stage two so instead we fold
everything everything into the bat
normalization later during training and
try to estimate these in the running
manner so that everything is a bit
simpler and that gives us the bat
normalization layer um and as I
mentioned no one likes this layer it
causes a huge amount of bugs um and
intuitively it's because it is coupling
examples um in the for pass of a neural
nut and uh I've shot myself in the foot
with this layer over and over again in
my life and I don't want you to suffer
the same uh so basically try to avoid it
as much as possible uh some of the other
alternatives to these layers are for
example group normalization or layer
normalization and those have become more
common uh in more recent deep learning
uh but we haven't covered those yet uh
but definitely bash normalization was
very influential at the time when it
came out in roughly 2015 because it was
kind of the first time that you could
train reliably uh much deeper neural
nuts and fundamentally the reason for
that is because this layer was very
effective at controlling the statistics
of the activations in the neural nut so
that's the story so far and um that's
all I wanted to cover and in the future
lectures hopefully we can start going
into recurrent R Nets and um recurring
neural Nets as we'll see are just very
very deep networks because you uh you
unroll the loop and uh when you actually
optimize these neurals and that's where
a lot of this
um analysis around the activation
statistics and all these normalization
layers will become very very important
for uh good performance so we'll see
that next time bye okay so I lied I
would like us to do one more summary
here as a bonus and I think it's useful
as to have one more summary of
everything I've presented in this
lecture but also I would like us to
start by torify our code a little bit so
it looks much more like what you would
encounter in PCH so you'll see that I
will structure our code into these
modules like a link
uh module and a borm module and I'm
putting the code inside these modules so
that we can construct neural networks
very much like we would construct them
in pytorch and I will go through this in
detail so we'll create our neural net
then we will do the optimization loop as
we did before and then the one more
thing that I want to do here is I want
to look at the activation statistics
both in the forward pass and in the
backward pass and then here we have the
evaluation and sampling just like before
so let me rewind all the way up here and
and go a little bit slower so here I
creating a linear layer you'll notice
that torch.nn has lots of different
types of layers and one of those layers
is the linear layer torch. n. linear
takes a number of input features output
features whether or not we should have a
bias and then the device that we want to
place this layer on and the data type so
I will emit these two but otherwise we
have the exact same thing we have the
fan in which is the number of inputs fan
out the number of outputs and whether or
not we want to use a bias
and internally inside this layer there's
a weight and a bias if you'd like it it
is typical to initialize the weight
using um say random numbers drawn from
aashan and then here's the coming
initialization um that we discussed
already in this lecture and that's a
good default and also the default that I
believe pytor chooses and by default the
bias is usually initialized to zeros now
when you call this module uh this will
basically calculate W * X plus b if you
have a b and then when you also call
that parameters on this module it will
return uh the tensors that are the
parameters of this layer now next we
have the bash normalization layer so
I've written that here and this is very
similar to pytorch nn. bashor 1D layer
as shown
here so I'm kind of um taking these
three parameters here the dimensionality
the Epsilon that we will use in the
division and the momentum that we will
use in keeping track of these running
stats the running mean and the running
variance um now py actually takes quite
a few more things but I'm assuming some
of their settings so for us Aline will
be true that means that we will be using
a gamma and beta after the normalization
the track running stats will be true so
we will be keeping track of the running
mean and the running variance in the in
the bat Norm our device by default is
the CPU and the data type by default is
uh float float
32 so those are the defaults otherwise
uh we are taking all the same parameters
in this bachom layer so first I'm just
saving them now here's something new
there's a doc training which by default
is true and pytorch andn modules also
have this attribute. training and that's
because many modules in borm is included
in that have a different Behavior
whether you are training your interet
and or whether you are running it in an
evaluation mode and calculating your
evaluation loss or using it for
inference on some test examples and
bashor is an example of this because
when we are training we are going to be
using the mean and the variance
estimated from the current batch but
during inference we are using the
running mean and running variance and so
also if we are training we are updating
mean and variance but if we are testing
then these are not being updated they're
kept fixed and so this flag is necessary
and by default true just like in
pytorch now the parameters of B 1D are
the gamma and the beta
here and then the running mean and
running variance are called buffers in
pyto
nomenclature and these buffers are
trained using exponential moving average
here explicitly and they are not part of
the back propagation and stochastic
radient descent so they are not sort of
like parameters of this layer and that's
why when we C when we have a parameters
here we only return gamma and beta we do
not return the mean and the variance
this is trained sort of like internally
here um every forward pass using
exponential moving average so that's the
initialization now in a forward pass if
we are training then we use the mean and
the variance estimated by the batch let
me pull up the paper
here we calculate the mean and the
variance now up above I was estimating
the standard deviation and keeping track
of the standard deviation here in the
running standard deviation instead of
running variance but let's follow the
paper exactly here they calculate the
variance which is the standard deviation
squared and that's what's get track of
in a running variance instead of a
running standard
deviation uh but those two would be very
very similar I
believe um if we are not training then
we use running mean and variance we
normalize and then here I am calculating
the output of this layer and I'm also
assigning it to an attribute called out
now out is something that I'm using in
our modules here uh this is not what you
would find in pytorch we are slightly
deviating from it I'm creating a DOT out
because I would like to very easily um
maintain all those variables so that we
can create statistics of them and plot
them but pytorch and modules will not
have a do out attribute and finally here
we are updating the buffers using again
as I mentioned exponential moving
average uh provide given the provided
momentum and importantly you'll notice
that I'm using the torch. nogra context
manager and I doing this because if we
don't use this then pytorch will start
building out an entire computational
graph out of these tensors because it is
expecting that we will eventually call
Dot backward but we are never going to
be calling dot backward on anything that
includes running mean and running
variance so that's why we need to use
this context manager so that we are not
um sort of maintaining them using all
this additional memory um so this will
make it more efficient and it's just
telling pyour that there will no
backward we just have a bunch of tensors
we want to update them that's it and
then we
return okay now scrolling down we have
the 10h layer this is very very similar
to uh torch. 10h and it doesn't do too
much it just calculates 10 as you might
expect so uh that's torch. 10h and uh
there's no parameters in this layer but
because these are layers um it now
becomes very easy to sort of like stack
them up into uh basically just a list um
and uh we can do all the initializations
that we're used to so we have the
initial sort of embedding Matrix we have
our layers and we can call them
sequentially and then again with Tor no
grb but there's some initializations
here so we want to make the output
softmax a bit less confident like we saw
and in addition to that because we are
using a six layer multi-layer percep on
here so you see how I'm stacking linear
10age linear Tage Etc uh I'm going to be
using the gain here and I'm going to
play with this in a second so you'll see
how uh when we change this what happens
to the
statistics finally the parameters are
basically the embedding Matrix and all
the parameters in all the layers and
notice here I'm using a double list
apprehension if you want to call it that
but for every layer in layers and for
every parameter in each of those layers
we are just stacking up all those piece
uh all those parameters now in total we
have 46,000 um
parameters and I'm telling P that all of
them require
gradient then here uh we have everything
here we are actually mostly used to uh
we are sampling a batch we are doing a
forward pass the forward pass now is
just the linear application of all the
layers in order followed by the cross
entropy and then in the backward pass
you'll notice that for every single
layer I now iterate over all the outputs
and I'm telling pytorch to retain the
gradient of them and then here we are
already used to uh all the all the
gradient set To None do the backward to
fill in the gradients uh do an update
using stochastic gradient sent and then
uh track some statistics and then I am
going to break after a single iteration
now here in this cell in this diagram I
I'm visualizing the histogram the
histograms of the for pass activations
and I'm specifically doing it at the 10
each layers so iterating over all the
layers except for the very last one
which is basically just the U soft Max
layer um if it is a 10h layer and I'm
using a 10h layer just because they have
a finite output netive 1 to 1 and so
it's very easy to visualize here so you
see 1 to one and it's a finite range and
easy to work with I take the out tensor
from that layer into T and then I'm
calculating the mean the standard
deviation and the percent saturation of
T and the way I Define the percent
saturation is that t. absolute value is
greater than 97 so that means we are
here at the tals of the 10 H and
remember that when we are in the tales
of the 10 H that will actually stop
gradients so we don't want this to be
too
high now here I'm calling torch.
histogram and then I am plotting this
histogram so basically what this is
doing is that every different type of
layer and they have a different color we
are looking at how many um values in
these tensors take on any of the values
Below on this axis here so the first
layer is fairly saturated uh here at 20%
so you can see that it's got Tails here
but then everything sort of stabilizes
and if we had more layers here it would
actually just stabilize at around the
standard deviation of about 65 and the
saturation would be roughly 5% and the
reason that the stabilizes and gives us
a nice distribution here is because gain
is set to 5
over3 now here this gain you see that by
default we initialize with 1 /un of fan
in but then here during initialization I
come in and I erator all the layers and
if it's a linear layer I boost that by
the gain now we saw that one so
basically if we just do not use a gain
then what happens if I redraw this you
will see that the standard deviation is
shrinking and the saturation is coming
to zero and basically what's happening
is the first layer is you know pretty
decent but then further layers are just
kind of like shrinking down to zero and
it's happening slowly but it's shrinking
to zero and the reason for that is when
you just have a sandwich of linear
layers alone then a then initializing
our weights in this manner we saw
previously would have conserved the
standard deviation of one but because we
have this interspersed 10 in layers in
there these 10h layers are squashing
functions and so they take your
distribution and they slightly squash it
and so some gain is necessary to keep
expanding it to fight the
squashing so it just turns out that 5
over3 is a good value so if we have
something too small like one we saw that
things will come toward zero but if it's
something too high let's do
two then here we see that um
well let me do something a bit more
extreme because so it's a bit more
visible let's try
three okay so we see here that the
saturations are going to be way too
large okay so three would create way too
saturated activations so 5 over3 is a
good setting for a sandwich of linear
layers with 10h activations and it
roughly stabilizes the standard
deviation at a reasonable point now
honestly I have no idea where 5 over3
came from in pytorch um when we were
looking at the coming initialization um
I see empirically that it stabilizes
this sandwich of linear an 10age and
that the saturation is in a good range
um but I don't actually know if this
came out of some math formula I tried
searching briefly for where this comes
from uh but I wasn't able to find
anything uh but certainly we see that
empirically these are very nice ranges
our saturation is roughly 5% which is a
pretty good number and uh this is a good
setting of The gain in this context
similarly we can do the exact same thing
with the gradients so here is a very
same Loop if it's a 10h but instead of
taking a layer do out I'm taking the
grad and then I'm also showing the mean
and the standard deviation and I'm
plotting the histogram of these values
and so you'll see that the gradient
distribution is uh fairly reasonable and
in particular what we're looking for is
that all the different layers in this
sandwich has roughly the same gradient
things are not shrinking or exploding so
uh we can for example come here and we
can take a look at what happens if this
gain was way too small so this was
0.5 then you see the first of all the
activations are shrinking to zero but
also the gradients are doing something
weird the gradients started out here and
then now they're like expanding
out and similarly if we for example have
a too high of a gain so like
three then we see that also the
gradients have there's some asymmetry
going on where as you go into deeper and
deeper layers the activation CS are
changing and so that's not what we want
and in this case we saw that without the
use of batro as we are going through
right now we had to very carefully set
those gains to get nice activations in
both the forward pass and the backward
pass now before we move on to bat
normalization I would also like to take
a look at what happens when we have no
10h units here so erasing all the 10
nonlinearities but keeping the gain at 5
over3 we now have just a giant linear
sandwich so let's see what happens to
the activations
as we saw before the correct gain here
is one that is the standard deviation
preserving gain so 1.66 7 is too high
and so what's going to happen now is the
following uh I have to change this to be
linear so we are because there's no more
10h layers and let me change this to
linear as
well so what we're seeing is um the
activations started out on the blue and
have by layer four become very diffuse
so what's happening to the activations
is this and with the gradients on the
top layer the activation the gradient
statistics are the purple and then they
diminish as you go down deeper in the
layers and so basically you have an
asymmetry like in the neuron net and you
might imagine that if you have very deep
neural networks say like 50 layers or
something like that this just uh this is
not a good place to be uh so that's why
before bash normalization this was
incredibly tricky to to set in
particular if this is too large of a
gain this happens and if it's too little
of a
gain then this happens so the opposite
of that basically happens here we have a
um shrinking and a uh diffusion
depending on which direction you look at
it from and so certainly this is not
what you want and in this case the
correct setting of The gain is exactly
one just like we're doing at
initialization and then we see that the
uh statistics for the forward and a
backward pass are well behaved and so
the reason I want to show you this is
that basically like getting neural nness
to train before these normalization
layers and before the use of advanced
optimizers like adom which we still have
to cover and residual connections and so
on uh training neurs basically looked
like this it's like a total Balancing
Act you have to make sure that
everything is precisely orchestrated and
you have to care about the activations
and the gradients and their statistics
and then maybe you can train something
uh but it was it was basically
impossible to train very deep networks
and this is fundamentally the the reason
for that you'd have to be very very
careful with your
initialization um the other point here
is you might be asking yourself by the
way I'm not sure if I covered this why
do we need these 10h layers at all uh
why do we include them and then have to
worry about the gain and uh the reason
for that of course is that if you just
have a stack of linear layers then
certainly we're getting very easily nice
activations and so on uh but this is
just massive linear sandwich and it
turns out that it collapses to a single
linear layer in terms of its uh
representation power so if you were to
plot the output as a function of the
input you're just getting a linear
function no matter how many linear
layers you stack up you still just end
up with a linear transformation all the
WX plus BS just collapse into a large WX
plus b with slightly different W's and
slightly different B um but
interestingly even though the forward
pass collapses to just a linear layer
because of back propagation and uh the
dynamics of the backward pass the
optimization natur is not identical you
actually end up with uh all kinds of
interesting um Dynamics in the backward
pass uh because of the uh the way the
chain Ru is calculating it and so
optimizing a linear layer by itself and
optimizing a sandwich of 10 linear
layers in both cases those are just a
linear transformation in the forward
pass but the training Dynamics would be
different and there's entire papers that
analyze in fact like infinitely layered
uh linear layers and and so on and so
there's a lot of things to that you can
play with
there uh but basically the tal
linearities allow us to
um turn this sandwich from just a
linear uh function into uh a neural
network that can in principle um
approximate any arbitrary function okay
so now I've reset the code to use the
linear tanh sandwich like before and I
reset everything so the gain is 5 over
three uh we can run a single step of
optimization and we can look at the
activation statistics of the forward
pass and the backward pass but I've
added one more plot here that I think is
really important to look at when you're
training your neural nuts and to
consider and ultimately what we're doing
is we're updating the parameters of the
neural nut so we care about the
parameters and their values and their
gradients so here what I'm doing is I'm
actually iterating over all the
parameters available and then I'm only
um restricting it to the two-dimensional
parameters which are basically the
weights of the linear layers and I'm
skipping the biases and I'm skipping the
um gamas and the betas in the bom just
for Simplicity but you can also take a
look at those as well but what's
happening with the weights is um
instructive by
itself so here we have all the different
weights their shapes uh so this is the
embedding layer the first linear layer
all the way to the very last linear
layer and then we have the mean the
standard deviation of all these
parameters the histogram and you can see
that actually doesn't look that amazing
so there's some trouble in Paradise even
though these gradients looked okay
there's something weird going on here
I'll get to that in a second and the
last thing here is the gradient to data
ratio so sometimes I like to visualize
this as well because what this gives you
a sense of is what is the scale of the
gradient compared to the scale of the
actual values and this is important
because we're going to end up taking a
step update um that is the learning rate
times the gradient onto the data
and so if the gradient has too large of
magnitude if the numbers in there are
too large compared to the numbers in
data then you'd be in trouble but in
this case the gradient to data is our
low numbers so the values inside grad
are 1,000 times smaller than the values
inside data in these weights most of
them now notably that is not true about
the last layer and so the last layer
actually here the output layer is a bit
of a troublemaker in the way that this
is currently arranged because you can
see that the um last layer here in pink
takes on values that are much larger
than some of the values inside um inside
the neural nut so the standard
deviations are roughly 1 and3 throughout
except for the last last uh layer which
actually has roughly one -2 standard
deviation of gradients and so the
gradients on the last layer are
currently about 100 times greater sorry
10 times greater than all the other
weights inside the neural net and so
that's problematic because in the simple
stochastic rting theend setup you would
be training this last layer about 10
times faster than you would be training
the other layers at
initialization now this actually like
kind of fixes itself a little bit if you
train for a bit longer so for example if
I greater than 1,000 only then do a
break let me reinitialize and then let
me do it 1,000 steps and after 1,000
steps we can look at the forward pass
okay so you see how the neurons are a
bit are saturating a bit and we can also
look at the backward pass but otherwise
they look good they're about equal and
there's no shrinking to zero or
exploding to Infinities and you can see
that here in the weights uh things are
also stabilizing a little bit so the
Tails of the last pink layer are
actually coming coming in during the
optimization but certainly this is like
a little bit of troubling especially if
you are using a very simple update rule
like stochastic gradient descent instead
of a modern Optimizer like Adam now I'd
like to show you one more plot that I
usually look at when I train neural
networks and basically the gradient to
data ratio is not actually that
informative because what matters at the
end is not the gradient to data ratio
but the update to the data ratio because
that is the amount by which we will
actually change the data in these
tensors so coming up here what I'd like
to do is I'd like to introduce a new
update to data uh ratio it's going to be
list and we're going to build it out
every single iteration and here I'd like
to keep track of basically the
ratio every single
iteration so without any gradients I'm
comparing the update which is learning
rate times the times the
gradient that is the update that we're
going to apply to every
parameter uh so see I'm iterating over
all the parameters and then I'm taking
the basically standard deviation of the
update we're going to apply and divided
by the um actual content the data of of
that parameter and its standard
deviation so this is the ratio of
basically how great are the updates to
the values in these tensors then we're
going to take a log of it and actually
I'd like to take a log
10 um just so it's a nicer
visualization um so we're going to be
basically looking at the exponents of uh
the of this division here and then that
item to pop out the float and we're
going to be keeping track of this for
all the parameters and adding it to
these UD answer so now let me
reinitialize and run a th iterations we
can look at the activations the
gradients and the parameter gradients as
we did before but now I have one more
plot here to
introduce and what's Happening Here is
we're are interval parameters and I'm
constraining it again like I did here to
just the
weights so the number of dimensions in
these sensors is two and then I'm
basically plotting all of these um
update ratios over time
so when I plot this I plot those ratios
and you can see that they evolve over
time during initialization they take on
certain values and then these updates s
of like start stabilizing usually during
training then the other thing that I'm
plotting here is I'm plotting here like
an approximate value that is a Rough
Guide for what it roughly should be and
it should be like roughly
one3 and so that means that basically
there's some values in the tensor um and
they take on certain values and the
updates to them at every iteration are
no more than roughly 1,000th of the
actual like magnitude in those tensors
uh if this was much larger like for
example if this was um if the log of
this was like say negative 1 this is
actually updating those values quite a
lot they're undergoing a lot of change
but the reason that the final rate the
final uh layer here is an outlier is
because this layer was artificially
shrunk down to keep the soft Max um
incom unconfident
so here you see how we multiplied The
Weight by
0.1 uh in the initialization to make the
last layer prediction less confident
that made that artificially made the
values inside that tensor way too low
and that's why we're getting temporarily
a very high ratio but you see that that
stabilizes over time once uh that weight
starts to learn starts to learn but
basically I like to look at the
evolution of this update ratio for all
my parameters usually and I like to make
sure that it's not too much above onean
neg3 roughly uh so around3 on this log
plot if it's below -3 usually that means
that the parameters are not trained fast
enough so if our learning rate was very
low let's do that
experiment uh let's initialize and then
let's actually do a learning rate of say
one3 here so
0.001 if your learning rate is way too
low
this plot will typically reveal it so
you see how all of these updates are way
too small so the size of the update is
uh basically uh 10,000 times um in
magnitude to the size of the numbers in
that tensor in the first place so this
is a symptom of training way too
slow so this is another way to sometimes
set the learning rate and to get a sense
of what that learning rate should be and
ultimately this is something that you
would uh keep track of
if anything the learning rate here is a
little bit on the higher side uh because
you see that um we're above the black
line of3 we're somewhere around -2.5
it's like okay and uh but everything is
like somewhat stabilizing and so this
looks like a pretty decent setting of of
um learning rates and so on but this is
something to look at and when things are
miscalibrated you will you will see very
quickly so for
example everything looks pretty well
behaved right but just as a comparison
when things are not properly calibrated
what does that look like let me come up
here and let's say that for example uh
what do we do let's say that we forgot
to apply this a fan in normalization so
the weights inside the linear layers are
just sampled from aaan and all the
stages what happens to our how do we
notice that something's off well the
activation plot will tell you whoa your
neurons are way too saturated uh the
gradients are going to be all messed up
uh the histogram for these weights are
going to be all messed up as well and
there's a lot of asymmetry and then if
we look here I suspect it's all going to
be also pretty messed up so uh you see
there's a lot of uh discrepancy in how
fast these layers are learning and some
of them are learning way too fast so uh1
1.5 those are very large numbers in
terms of this ratio again you should be
somewhere around3 and not much more
about that um so this is how
miscalibrations of your neuron nuts are
going to manifest and these kinds of
plots here are a good way of um sort of
bringing um those miscalibrations sort
of uh to your attention and so you can
address them okay so so far we've seen
that when we have this linear tanh
sandwich we can actually precisely
calibrate the gains and make the
activations the gradients and the
parameters and the updates all look
pretty decent but it definitely feels a
little bit like balancing of a pencil on
your finger and that's because this gain
has to be very precisely calibrated so
now let's introduce bat normalization
layers into the fix into the mix and
let's let's see how that helps fix the
problem so
here I'm going to take the bachom 1D
class and I'm going to start placing it
inside and as I mentioned before the
standard typical place you would place
it is between the linear layer so right
after it but before the nonlinearity but
people have definitely played with that
and uh in fact you can get very similar
results even if you place it after the
nonlinearity um and the other thing that
I wanted to mention is it's totally fine
to also place it at the end uh after the
last linear layer and before the L
function so this is potentially fine as
well um and in this case this would be
output would be WAP
size um now because the last layer is
Bash we would not be changing the weight
to make the softmax less confident we'd
be changing the gamma because gamma
remember in the bathroom is the variable
that multiplicatively interacts with the
output of that
normalization so we can initialize this
sandwich now we can train and we can see
that the activations uh are going to of
course look uh very good and they are
going to necessarily look good because
now before every single 10h layer there
is a normalization in the bashor so this
is unsurprisingly all uh looks pretty
good it's going to be standard deviation
of roughly 65 2% and roughly equal
standard deviation throughout the entire
layers so everything looks very
homogeneous the gradients look good the
weights look good and their
distributions and then the
updates also look um pretty reasonable
uh we are going above3 a little bit but
not by too much so all the parameters
are training at roughly the same rate um
here
but now what we've gained is um we are
going to be slightly less
um brittle with respect to the gain of
these so for example I can make the gain
be say2 here um which is much much much
slower than what we had with the tan
H but as we'll see the activations will
actually be exactly unaffected uh and
that's because of again this explicit
normalization the gradients are going to
look okay the weight gradients are going
to look okay okay but actually the
updates will
change and so even though the forward
and backward pass to a very large extent
look okay because of the backward pass
of the Bator and how the scale of the
incoming activations interacts in the
Bator and its uh backward pass this is
actually changing the um the scale of
the updates on these parameters so the
grades on gradients of these weights are
affected so we still don't get it
completely free pass to pass in arbitral
um weights here but it everything else
is significantly more robust in terms of
the forward backward and the weight
gradients it's just that you may have to
retune your learning rate if you are
changing sufficiently the the scale of
the activations that are coming into the
batch Norms so here for example this um
we changed the gains of these linear
layers to be greater and we're seeing
that the updates are coming out lower as
a
result and then finally we can also so
if we are using borms we don't actually
need to necessarily let me reset this to
one so there's no gain we don't
necessarily even have to um normalize by
fan in sometimes so if I take out the
fan in so these are just now uh random
gsh in we'll see that because of borm
this will actually be relatively well
behaved
so the statistic look of course in the
forward pass look good the gradients
look good the uh backward uh the weight
updates look okay A little bit of fat
tails on some of the
layers and uh this looks okay as well
but as you as you can see uh we're
significantly below ne3 so we'd have to
bump up the learning rate of this bachor
uh so that we are training more properly
and in particular looking at this
roughly looks like we have to 10x the
learning rate to get to about
one3 so we' come here and we would
change this to be update of 1.0 and if I
reinitialize
then we'll see that everything still of
course looks good and now we are roughly
here and we expect this to be an okay
training run so long story short we are
significantly more robust to the gain of
these linear layers whether or not we
have to apply the fan in and then we can
change the gain uh but we actually do
have to worry a little bit about the
update um scales and making sure that uh
the learning rate is properly calibrated
here but this the activations of the
forward backward pass and the updates
are are looking significantly more well
behaved except for the global scale that
is potentially being adjusted here okay
so now let me summarize there are three
things I was hoping to achieve with this
section number one I wanted to introduce
you to bat normalization which is one of
the first modern innovations that we're
looking into that helped stabilize very
deep neural networks and their training
and I hope you understand how the B
normalization works and um how it would
be used in a neural network number two I
was hoping to py torify some of our code
and wrap it up into these uh modules so
like linear bash 1D 10h Etc these are
layers or modules and they can be
stacked up into neural nuts like Lego
building blocks and these layers
actually exist in pytorch and if you
import torch NN then you can actually
the way I've constructed it you can
simply just use pytorch by prepending n
and Dot to all these different
layers and actually everything will just
work because the API that I've developed
here is identical to the API that
pytorch uses and the implementation also
is basically as far as I'm Weare
identical to the one in pytorch and
number three I tried to introduce you to
the diagnostic tools that you would use
to understand whether your neural
network is in a good State dynamically
so we are looking at the statistics and
histograms and activation of the forward
pass activ activations the backward pass
gradients and then also we're looking at
the weights that are going to be updated
as part of stochastic gradi in ascent
and we're looking at their means
standard deviations and also the ratio
of gradients to data or even better the
updates to data and we saw that
typically we don't actually look at it
as a single snapshot Frozen in time at
some particular iteration typically
people look at this as a over time just
like I've done here and they look at
these update to data ratios and they
make sure everything looks okay and in
particular I said said that um
W3 or basically ne3 on the lock scale is
a good uh rough euristic for what you
want this ratio to be and if it's way
too high then probably the learning rate
or the updates are a little too too big
and if it's way too small that the
learning rate is probably too small so
that's just some of the things that you
may want to play with when you try to
get your neural network to uh work with
very
well now there's a number of things I
did not try to achieve I did not try to
beat our previous performance as an
example by introducing using the bash
layer actually I did try um and I found
the new I used the learning rate finding
mechanism that I've described before I
tried to train a borm layer a borm
neural nut and uh I actually ended up
with results that are very very similar
to what we've obtained before and that's
because our performance now is not
bottlenecked by the optimization which
is what borm is helping with the
performance at this stage is bottleneck
by what I suspect is the context length
of our context so currently we are
taking three characters to predict the
fourth one and I think we need to go
beyond that and we need to look at more
powerful architectures like recurrent
neural networks and Transformers in
order to further push um the lock
probabilities that we're achieving on
this data
set and I also did not try to have a
full explanation of all of these
activations the gradients and the
backward pass and the statistics of all
these gradients and so you may have
found some of the parts here un
intuitive and maybe you're slightly
confused about okay if I change the uh
gain here how come that we need a
different learning rate and I didn't go
into the full detail because you'd have
to actually look at the backward pass of
all these different layers and get an
intuitive understanding of how that
works and I did not go into that in this
lecture the purpose really was just to
introduce you to the diagnostic tools
and what they look like but there's
still a lot of work remaining on the
intuitive level to understand the
initialization the backward pass and how
all of that interacts uh but you
shouldn't feel too bad because honestly
we are getting to The Cutting Edge of
where the field is
we certainly haven't I would say soled
initialization and we haven't soled back
propagation and these are still very
much an active area of research people
are still trying to figure out what is
the best way to initialize these
networks what is the best update rule to
use um and so on so none of this is
really solved and we don't really have
all the answers to all the to you know
all these cases but at least uh you know
we're making progress and at least we
have some tools to tell us uh whether or
not things are on the right track for
now so
I think we've made positive progress in
this lecture and I hope you enjoyed that
and I will see you next time